A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests, Series E FA314
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Organizations and Parks
  - Organizations and Parks - Hudson River Conservation Society, 1956-1961 (Box 62, Folder 0623A)
  - Organizations and Parks - Hudson River Conservation Society - Contributions, 1940-1961 (Box 62, Folder 624)
    Contributions by John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, toward Society projects.
  - Organizations and Parks - Hudson River Conservation Society - Crugers Mansion, 1940-1963 (Box 63, Folder 625)
    Attempts to interest John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Laurance S. Rockefeller in mansion restoration failed; mansion restored by local committees. Crugers Mansion later became known as Boscobel.
  - Organizations and Parks - Hudson River Conservation Society - Crugers Mansion, 1940-1963 (Box 63, Folder 0625A)
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House, 1940-1953 (Box 63, Folder 626)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest in Manor House aroused through Hudson River Conservation Society; Hugh Grant Rowell's advice; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s visit to House. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest maintained until 1953, when he purchased it; decision to restore it. House turned over to Sleepy Hollow Restorations when restorations completed. Negotiations with local governments. Correspondents include Hugh Grant Rowell, Lester Sleinkofer, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    169H51
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House, 1953-1955 (Box 63, Folder 627)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest in Manor House aroused through Hudson River Conservation Society; Hugh Grant Rowell's advice; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s visit to House. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s interest maintained until 1953, when he purchased it; decision to restore it. House turned over to Sleepy Hollow Restorations when restorations completed. Negotiations with local governments. Map enclosed. Correspondents include Hugh Grant Rowell, Lester Sleinkofer, Dana S. Creel, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House, 1955-1959 (Box 63, Folder 628)
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House, 1955-1959 (Box 63, Folder 0628A)
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House - Letters of Appreciation, 1953-1961 (Box 63, Folder 629)
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House - Opening, 1959 (Box 63, Folder 630)
    Preparations; transcript of proceedings; Nelson A. Rockefeller speech; photographs.
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House - Insurance, 1955-1957 (Box 64, Folder 631)
    Coverage while restoration work going on.
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House - Re-zoning, 1953-1955 (Box 64, Folder 632)
    Change made to put Manor in "limited business" zone.
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House - Deed to Sleepy Hollow Restorations, 1958-1959 (Box 64, Folder 633)
    Terms of transfer; $1,000,000 gift to aid in maintenance.
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House - Letters of Suggestions, Offering Gifts, Etc., 1953-1959 (Box 64, Folder 634)
    Miscellaneous offers of pictures and articles; requests for positions.
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House - Publicity, 1944-1954 (Box 64, Folder 635)
    Newspaper clippings on House and property; reports of sales, plans, progress of restoration, and significance.
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House - Publicity, 1955-1960 (Box 64, Folder 636)
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House - Purchase of Property, 1953-1957 (Box 64, Folder 637)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. purchased property from Harmon-Croton Golf Range in 1953; details of purchase; purchases of additional land to round out property. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., William J. Yates.
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor House - Purchase of Property, 1957-1960 (Box 64, Folder 638)
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor - Acker Purchase (Ferryhouse), 1955-1957 (Box 65, Folder 639)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. purchased ferry house and site to add to Manor restoration. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., William Yates, John Graham.
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor - Colonial Williamsburg Consultants, 1953-1954 (Box 65, Folder 640)
    Reports on progress of experts' study of history of Manor House; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s close interest in work. Furnishing of House. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., A. S. Kendrew, John Graham.
  - Organizations and Parks - Van Cortlandt Manor - Colonial Williamsburg Consultants, 1955-1959 (Box 65, Folder 641)
  - Organizations and Parks - Cordell Hull Foundation, 1951-1961 (Box 65, Folder 642)
    Organized to provide scholarships for Latin American students at the Nashville, Tennessee University Center. Appeals declined. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Robert Bates.
    169H6
  - Organizations and Parks - Indian Associations, 1938-1961 (Box 65, Folder 643)
    Appeals for aid declined. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. interest in preserving pueblos from flooding caused by building of dams in Southwest; correspondence with Secretary of the Interior Harold L. Ickes. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Harold L. Ickes, Horace Albright.
    169In
  - Organizations and Parks - Indian Associations - North American Indian Fund, 1920-1925 (Box 65, Folder 644)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gives $1,000 toward cost of volume on history of American Indians.
  - Organizations and Parks - Indian Associations - American Indian Defense Association, 1923-1925 (Box 65, Folder 645)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $1,000, 1924; later appeals declined.
  - Organizations and Parks - Indian Rights Association, 1924-1958 (Box 65, Folder 646)
    Oldest Indian welfare organization in United States. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $9,000, 1924. Controversy between several Indian welfare groups over religious liberty. Later requests declined. Correspondents include Arthur Woods, Kenneth Chorley.
    169In2
  - Organizations and Parks - Institute of International Education, 1926-1952 (Box 66, Folder 647)
    Student and professor exchange program, supported mainly by Carnegie and Ford grants. Family interest in Institute's activities; declinations of most invitations and appeals. Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial and Rockefeller Brothers Fund grants; occasional personal contributions. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, Dr. Stephen Duggan, Laurance Duggan, Kenneth Holland, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    169In3
  - Organizations and Parks - Institute of International Education, 1926-1952 (Box 66, Folder 0647A)
  - Organizations and Parks - Institute of International Education, 1953-1961 (Box 66, Folder 648)
    Student and professor exchange program, supported mainly by Carnegie and Ford grants. Family interest in Institute's activities; declinations of most invitations and appeals. Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial and Rockefeller Brothers Fund grants; occasional personal contributions. John D. Rockefeller 3rd spoke at Institute dinner, 1955. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, Dr. Stephen Duggan, Laurance Duggan, Kenneth Holland, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Organizations and Parks - Institute of International Education, 1953-1961 (Box 66, Folder 0648A)
    David Rockefeller spoke at Institute dinner, 1953. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Organizations and Parks - Institute of International Education - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Address, 1955-1956 (Box 66, Folder 649)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd chief speaker at Houston dinner sponsored by Institute of International Education. Copy of his address.
  - Organizations and Parks - Institute of International Education - Wieschhoff Memorial Fund, 1961 (Box 66, Folder 650)
    Tribute to Wieschhoff of New York, who was killed with Dag Hammerskjold. Various members of family gave to fund for African student exchange program.
  - Organizations and Parks - Indian Tribal Arts Exposition, 1931-1934 (Box 66, Folder 651)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller contributed to expenses of art display in New York City. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller.
    169In4
  - Organizations and Parks - Interscience Foundation, 1946-1950 (Box 66, Folder 652)
    Organized to advance low-cost housing through the Community Development Trust Program. Opposed federal aid as socialism. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Frederick Briggs.
    169In6
  - Organizations and Parks - Interscience Foundation, 1946-1950 (Box 66, Folder 0652A)
    Efforts to interest David Rockefeller in work failed. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Organizations and Parks - Association on American Indian Affairs, Inc., 1933-1961 (Box 66, Folder 653)
    Organized to work with the Bureau of Indian Affairs to improve life of reservation Indians; stressed health and economic welfare. After World War II, emphasis on citizenship rights. Rockefeller Brothers Fund contributions. Correspondents include Oliver LaFarge, Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    169In7
  - Organizations and Parks - Association on American Indian Affairs, Inc., 1933-1961 (Box 66, Folder 0653A)
  - Organizations and Parks - Italy-America Society, 1918-1947 (Box 66, Folder 654)
    Charles Evans Hughes invited John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to join Society of Italian-American friendship. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $1,000 in 1918; no real interest after this initial gift. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
    169It
  - Organizations and Parks - Izaak Walton League of America, Inc., 1925-1960 (Box 67, Folder 655)
    Conservation group gave tribute to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. for his conservation work. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $5,000 toward conservation work on Public Lands, 1947-1948. League gave Laurance S. Rockefeller information in connection with work of ORRRC. Correspondents include Kenneth Chorley, Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Carl O. Gustafson.
    169Iz
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. invited to membership, 1907; declined this and various other appeals and invitation. No material for 1923-1951. In 1951, John D. Rockefeller 3rd became interested in newly reviving Society. Early memos on what kind of program new Society should attempt: cultural exchange, a meeting place for those interested in Japan - catalyst-type activity. In 1952, John D. Rockefeller 3rd became president; John Foster Dulles, Chairman of Board till 1952. Early activities setting up program, membership, etc. Doug Overton became Executive Secretary. John D. Rockefeller 3rd 1953 article regarding Society. Overton memos on budget and activities; polls on American attitude toward Japan; miscellaneous correspondence; scholarships; membership lists. 1956 monograph on Japanese economy; 1957 Annual Report; 1961 Address by Douglas MacArthur, Jr.; 1961 Japan Societies Conference. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Don McLean, Jr., Douglas Overton, Raymond Kramer, Kenneth Holland, Edgar B. Young.
    169J
    - 1907-May 1952 (Box 67, Folder 656)
    - June-December 1952 (Box 67, Folder 657)
    - January-July 1953 (Box 67, Folder 658)
    - August-December 1953 (Box 67, Folder 659)
    - January-June 1954 (Box 67, Folder 660)
    - July-December 1954 (Box 68, Folder 661)
    - 1955-March 1956 (Box 68, Folder 662)
    - April-October 1956 (Box 68, Folder 663)
    - November 1956-June 1958 (Box 68, Folder 664)
    - July 1958-June 1959 (Box 68, Folder 665)
    - July 1959-August 1960 (Box 69, Folder 666)
    - September 1960-April 1961 (Box 69, Folder 667)
    - May-December 1961 (Box 69, Folder 668)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Student Fellowship Program, 1958-1959 (Box 69, Folder 669)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd's letters of appeal asking for contributions to program. Problems of privately sponsored Japanese students in United States.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Yoshida, 1954 (Box 69, Folder 670)
    Japanese Prime Minister's visit to United States; arrangements for dinner at which John D. Rockefeller 3rd presided.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Personnel, 1952-1958 (Box 69, Folder 671)
    Hiring of Douglas Overton; consideration of other candidates for jobs.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Reports, 1952-1959 (Box 70, Folder 672)
    Mimeographed reports to directors and members.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Fujiwara Opera Cast Reception, 1952 (Box 70, Folder 673)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd hosted reception for Japanese company; arrangements.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Luncheon for Aiichiro Fujiyama, 1958 (Box 70, Folder 674)
    For Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Luncheon for Jun Tsuchiya, 1954 (Box 70, Folder 675)
    For Consul General.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Luncheon for Ambassador Kase, 1956 (Box 70, Folder 676)
    Permanent Observer to the United Nations.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Dinner for Prime Minister Nobusuke Kishi, 1957 (Box 70, Folder 677)
    Arrangements for Prime Minister's visit.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Luncheon for Mamoru Shigemitsu, 1955 (Box 70, Folder 678)
    Luncheon for Foreign Minister.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Luncheon for R. Sawada, June 1953 (Box 70, Folder 679)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Dinner for Shigeru Yoshida, 1960 (Box 70, Folder 680)
    Arrangements; Yoshida's gift to Japan Society of Japanese books.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Dinner for Ambassador Araki, 1952 (Box 70, Folder 681)
    First post-war ambassador to United States.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Dinner for Ambassador Iguchi, 1954 (Box 70, Folder 682)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Dinner for Ambassador Tani, 1956 (Box 70, Folder 683)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Dinner for Ambassador Tsushima, 1952 (Box 70, Folder 684)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Luncheon for Prime Minister Ikeda, 1961 (Box 70, Folder 685)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Benefit and Retirement Plan, 1957 (Box 70, Folder 686)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Budgets, 1957-1961 (Box 71, Folder 687)
    Copies only.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Board of Directors, 1952-1961 (Box 71, Folder 688)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd correspondence with new members and with retiring members.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Certificate of Incorporation and By-Laws, 1952 (Box 71, Folder 689)
    Development of new by-laws with cooperation of John D. Rockefeller 3rd's office; copies of Articles of Incorporation.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Committee on Cultural Interchange, 1952-1956 (Box 71, Folder 690)
    Committee's policies, proposals for activities, program. Okinawan problems. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Douglas Overton.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Committee on Cultural Interchange - Intellectual Interchange, 1957-1961 (Box 71, Folder 691)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Contributions, 1924-1925, 1958-1961 (Box 71, Folder 692)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. 1925 pledge cancelled. Contributions by Abby Rockefeller Mauzé. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Contributions, 1924-1925, 1958-1961 (Box 71, Folder 692A)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Contributions, 1952-1960 (Box 71, Folder 693)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd began contributions at $5,000 a year plus extra gifts for special purposes; annual giving exceeded $35,000 a year. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Douglas Overton.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Contributions, 1960-1962 (Box 71, Folder 694)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Entertainment for Crown Prince Akihito, 1953 (Box 72, Folder 695)
    Arrangements for Crown Prince's visit. Dinner at Waldorf with John D. Rockefeller 3rd presiding. Crown Prince spent three days at Jackson Hole ranch. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Douglas Overton.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Entertainment for Crown Prince Akihito, 1953 (Box 72, Folder 696)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Entertainment for Crown Prince Akihito, 1953 (Box 72, Folder 697)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Dinner for Crown Prince Akihito, 1960 (Box 72, Folder 698)
    Invitations; suggestions; copy of John D. Rockefeller 3rd's address.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Letters of Appeal and Miscellaneous Contributions, 1952-1962 (Box 72, Folder 699)
    Lists of sustaining members (business concerns); memos regarding fund-raising and finances. John D. Rockefeller 3rd letters of appeal to companies; their contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Letters of Appeal and Miscellaneous Contributions, 1952-1962 (Box 72, Folder 700)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Letters of Appeal and Miscellaneous Contributions, 1952-1962 (Box 73, Folder 701)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 73, Folder 702)
    Mimeographed copies of minutes of meetings of members and board of directors; not a complete set.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Minutes, 1954-1956 (Box 73, Folder 703)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Minutes, 1957-1958 (Box 73, Folder 704)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Japanese Scholars Project Report, 1958 (Box 73, Folder 705)
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Publicity, 1952-1961 (Box 74, Folder 706)
    Drafting of a 1952 memo announcing John D. Rockefeller 3rd's election as president. One 1961 newspaper story on Society. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Financial Statements, 1953-1961 (Box 74, Folder 707)
    Financial statements.
  - Organizations and Parks - Japan Society - Japan Society of Seattle, 1954-1958 (Box 74, Folder 708)
    In 1957, John D. Rockefeller 3rd addresses Society on "Expanding Foreign Trade - Opportunity and Necessity." Printed in Congressional Record; requests for magazine article declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Organizations and Parks - Junior Achievement, Inc., 1929-1961 (Box 74, Folder 709)
    Organized to give teenagers practical and sound business and economic training by having them run their own companies in neighborhood centers. All appeals declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    169J8
  - Organizations and Parks - Junior League of the City of New York, 1928-1961 (Box 74, Folder 710)
    League of wealthy women doing social service work in their leisure time puts out bond issue to buy new clubhouse, 1928; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. bought part of issue. Mary French Rockefeller a member. Saturday Evening Post article on League, 1948. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, Mary French Rockefeller.
    169J9
  - Organizations and Parks - Knickerbocker Greys, 1933-1956 (Box 74, Folder 711)
    Pre-boarding school boys' military organization dedicated to "spartan training," drilling in Central Park. John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Rodman Rockefeller were members. Laurance S. Rockefeller contributions; other appeals declined. Correspondents include Allan Smith, Henry Barclay, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    169K
  - Organizations and Parks - Koinonia Foundation, 1952-1958 (Box 74, Folder 712)
    Recruiting and training of individuals to work in Point 4 activities abroad. Organizational difficulties. No Rockefeller involvement. Correspondents include Frank Laubach, Clayton Lane, Dana S. Creel.
    169K1
  - Organizations and Parks - League of Neighbors-Fellowship of Faiths, 1926-1956 (Box 74, Folder 713)
    "Non-controversial" work for peace and international unity through a number of vague activities; all appeals declined, no Rockefeller interest. Organization later called World Fellowship of Faiths. Correspondents include Thomas B. Appleget, Willard S. Richardson, Charles Weller.
    169L
  - Organizations and Parks - League of Neighbors-Fellowship of Faiths - World Fellowship, Inc., 1940-1951 (Box 75, Folder 714)
    Group operated New Hampshire camp, organized discussions of "Ideals for World Government." No family interest.
  - Organizations and Parks - Mediaeval Academy of America, 1926-1958 (Box 75, Folder 715)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $5,000 to Academy for publication program, 1926. Later appeals declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    169M
  - Organizations and Parks - Menninger Foundation and Sanitarium; Southard School, 1940-1945 (Box 75, Folder 716)
    School for treatment of problem children; clinic for mentally disturbed, training of psychiatrists, etc. Papers and letters on role of psychiatry; juvenile delinquency. 1945 copy of Bulletin. Contributions by Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller, Abby Rockefeller Mauze, and Rockefeller Brothers Fund. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller, Karl Menninger, John Stone, Oren Root.
    169M1
    Open per DA 07/12/2008.
  - Organizations and Parks - Menninger Foundation and Sanitarium; Southard School, 1946-1961 (Box 75, Folder 717)
    School for treatment of problem children; clinic for mentally disturbed, training of psychiatrists, etc. Papers and letters on role of psychiatry; juvenile delinquency. 1959-1960 Report. Contributions by Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller, Abby Rockefeller Mauze, and Rockefeller Brothers Fund. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller, Karl Menninger, John Stone, Oren Root.
  - Organizations and Parks - Menninger Foundation and Sanitarium; Southard School, 1946-1961 (Box 75, Folder 0717A)
    Contributions by David Rockefeller. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Organizations and Parks - Michael Friedsam Foundation, 1939-1957 (Box 75, Folder 718)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. given medal for contributions to world of art, 1939, by group which was part of the Architectural League of New York; given second special medal, 1956. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    169M4
  - Organizations and Parks - Municipal Art Society, 1934-1956 (Box 75, Folder 719)
    Organized to foster plans to keep New York beautiful. Laurance S. Rockefeller made small contribution and was made a life member. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    169M5
  - Organizations and Parks - Municipal Art Society, 1934-1956 (Box 75, Folder 0719A)
    David Rockefeller given Scroll of Honor for work on Morningside Heights, 1956. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Organizations and Parks - Municipal Art Center, 1934-1937 (Box 75, Folder 720)